Hey, hey. What's up, my friend?
So, I have been trading for more a
decade now, man. Man, time flies.
And I've learned a few things along the
way. For example, like how to lose money
with one click, how to piss off your
wife at 4:00 a.m. in the morning, and
sometimes even how to do both at the
same time. Try to beat that. Yeah. So,
I've been there trading for 15 years and
I've made the mistakes, listened to the
wrong advice, and paid the price.
But hey, I'm still here shooting this
video.
That explains the importance of risk
management. Hint hint. So, in today's
video, you will learn what I wish
someone had told me when I was first
starting out.
There is no fluff. There is no hype.
There is no lumbos. Okay? Just the real
truths that I've learned over the last
15 years. Sounds good? Then let's get
started.
First, you must have an H in the markets
or rather your trading system. Your
trading strategy must have an H. You
might be wondering, man, Rainer, what is
an H? An H is something that you do
repeatedly that yields a profit over
time, otherwise also known as a positive
expectancy.
And by the way, if your age is using 19
indicators on your chart, you don't have
a strategy. You've got a Christmas tree.
Okay. So, how do you then define an age?
So you can define an age using this
mathematical formula. Don't don't freak
out, right? Because it's simple that
even a 12 year old can figure this one.
So E right stands for either expectancy
or your age is equals to your winning
percentage multiply by your average gain
minus your losing percentage multiply by
your average loss. I'll walk you through
an example so you can see how this this
works.
So let's say you have a trading system
that has a 70% winning rate. Your
average gain is $80 and your losing rate
is 30%. Why 30%? Because you know 100%
minus 70% you'll get 30%. So that's your
losing rate. And let's say your average
loss is $100 per trade. So what you're
going to do is to plug in these numbers
into the formula I just shared with you
earlier. So this is your winning rate
multiply by your average gain, your
losing rate multiply by your average
loss, and you'll get $26 per trade. So
this means right what does this $26
means? This means that you can expect to
earn an average of $26 per trade. So
let's say you have taken 100 trades
using the using this trading system.
What you're going to find is that you
will have about $2,600 right after
taking 100 trades. So this is what it
means to have a positive expectancy and
this is what it means to have an H in
the markets. Your E right your
expectancy has to be positive. If it's
negative then clearly you don't have an
H and the more you trade the more you
will lose. Now a question for you which
is more important your winning rate or
the risk-to-reward ratio? I'll give you
five seconds. One, two, three, four,
five. Okay, the answer is this. The most
important metric is it's a trick
question. Actually, both of them are
equally important because on its own,
let's say on its own, your winning rate
is meaningless because you can have a
90% winning rate, a 95% winning rate,
but let's say every time you win, you
win a dollar, but every time you lose,
you lose $100. So despite having a very
high winning rate, you still have a
unprofitable trading system. And
likewise, it's true, you can have a
amazing risk-to-reward ratio. Let's say,
let's say every time you risk a dollar,
you make $3 back, right? Quite a
favorable risk-to-reward ratio on your
trades. But what if your winning rate is
only 10%. Then what use is that? You
still have a unprofitable trading
system. So to know whether your trading
system has an age in the markets to know
whether you have a positive expectancy
both your winning rate and
risk-to-reward ratio they you must
combine them because both of them
matters. Okay. Now you know that having
an H is important. Okay. But to be a
consistently profitable trader you still
need this.
Next up you must master risk management.
This is, if you ask me, the lowest
hanging fruit that you can tackle in
trading that will pay you dividends for
the rest of your trading career. Because
it doesn't matter if you're if it's your
first day trading or your 20th year
trading because risk management
is something that you need on your first
day, first day of trading as well as
your last day of trading. So what does
risk management means in trading? Risk
management means right that you're able
to protect your downside no matter what
happens in your trading. Whether you
have five losing trades, 10 losing
trades, 20 losing trades in a row, guess
what? If you have sound risk management,
you should be able to survive and to
live to fight another day. Because
without sound risk management, even the
best trading system, even a profitable
trading system will fail. Let me give
you an example. This is so important
that I must hammer home this concept. So
imagine this. Imagine there are two
traders, John and Sally. They both have
a $10,000 trading account. So they have
the same size trading account. And let's
say they trade the same trading system.
And the trading system has a 50% winning
rate. Let's say on average they make a
an average of a 1:3 risk-reward ratio.
So let's say for example if you risk
$100 and you earn a 1 to3 riskreward
ratio it means that you would have
gotten $300 right for a winning trade on
average. And John, he's a kind of trader
that goes big or goes home. So he risk
$5,000 per trade which is about 50% of
his account. And Sally is a more a lot
more conservative. She risk 1% of her
account, right? $100 of 10K is 1%. And
also let's assume the outcome of the
next 10 trades are this right? The first
trade is a loser, second is loser,
loser, loser, loser, and then win win
win. So basically you encounter five
losing trades in a row before you
experience the winners. Now how would
the result fare for both traders? So
let's look at John. So John, you know
that he risk $5,000 per trade. So first
trade is a loser, second trade is a
loser. So minus 5K and minus 5K. You can
see that John is pretty much wiped out.
He's blown up, right? He has blown up
his account because he was too
aggressive in his in placing his trades.
Too much taking too much risk on his
trade. What about Sally? Okay, so you
can see Sally, she risk $100 per trade.
So first five trades are loser. One,
two, three, four, five. And you know
that she risk $100 per trade. So her
total loss, right, will amount to
something like $500.
Okay. But because she has proper risk
management, she leaves, she leave to
fight another day. So you can see that
she get to experience the profits that
will come her way and she experienced
this next five winning trades. 1 2 3 4 5
and as you know this system has an
average of a 1:3 riskreward ratio. This
means on average she wins $300 per trade
and she had five winning trades over
here. So in total it's about $1,500 over
here. So,55 you minus the initial loss
she experienced
you can see that in total Sally would
have made a profit of $1,000
a 10% gain on her account whereas John
he blew up right because he took on too
much risk so by now I want you to see
that risk management is key because you
can have a profitable trading system you
can have the best trading system in the
world but if you don't have proper risk
management
you will still lose because you're not
giving your trading system a chance for
it to play out its edge in the long run.
Now, if you are like John, right, you
risk 30, 40, 50% of your account on one
trade, then my advice to you is to go to
Vegas. You know, at least they give you
free drinks, right? While you lose
everything. Okay, moving on.
Trading psychology is not the answer. So
let me explain why. So often right
you've been told that you know trading
is 80% psychology man. You know you need
to master your emotions.
You need to follow your rules. You need
to be more disciplined.
So imagine this. Imagine you go down to
a casino and you bring along the best
psychologist, the best hypnotist that
you can find to help you be a
disciplined gambler, someone who follow
the rules of your betting system.
Let me ask you, will you profit against
the casino in the long run?
And I'm sure that you would agree the
answer is no. Of course not. Why is
that? And the reason is because you
don't have an edge over the casino. You
don't have an edge over the house. In
other words, you can master your trading
psychology that you look and feel like a
monk. But if you don't have an edge, it
doesn't matter because you will still
lose consistently. Agree?
So now the question is this. What is
successful trading about? If it's not
about psychology, it's this. Okay, I've
broken it down into this formula. This
is what I call the trading success
formula. So, trading success is when you
have an age, sound risk management, and
the discipline to follow your rules. And
by the way, you must have all three
ingredients. You can't let's say you
have an an age, but you don't have sound
risk management. Then what's going to
happen is that you'll eventually blow up
your account. Like like John earlier, he
has an age, but because he didn't have
sound risk management, he blew up.
That's what happens when you have an age
without sound risk management. What if
you have let's say risk management and
discipline but no age? Then what you're
going to do what is going to happen is
that you will suffer death by a thousand
cards. You have risk management in place
but because without an age you slowly
bleed your account over time till
there's nothing left. And what if you
have an age and risk management but no
discipline? Well, in this case you get
inconsistent results.
So as you can see right in order to be a
profitable trader a successful
consistently profitable trader all three
factors or ingredients are required.
So my point of view is that trading is
20% psychology because when you have an
age and sound risk management your
discipline will naturally take care of
itself. Right from from the hundreds of
students that I've trained, usually when
they have an age in sound risk
management, I don't really hear them or
complaining to me, "Hey, Raina, I'm
struggling with discipline." All the
discipline issues naturally melt away.
And for example, imagine this to prove
my point, right? Imagine that you have a
coin. Every time you toss the coin, it
comes up hits. You win $100. Every time
it comes up tails, you lose $50. Let me
ask you, will you struggle to toss the
coin? Will you feel that after three
tails in a row, you struggle? Ah man,
Reena, I can't seem to toss the coin the
fourth times. What if I lose? I think
99% of the population will won't face
that problem. And if you happen to face
that problem problem, it means that the
loss that you're taking is too much. You
probably want to dial back down your
risk instead of maybe losing $50 on each
toy cost to coin coin toss. You want to
maybe reduce down your bet size to maybe
$10 or $20 to a level that you're
comfortable with because as you can see
once you have an age, once you have a
sound risk management, most people, most
traders will not face issues with
trading psychology. And for those people
who tell you that trading, no, trading
is 80% psychology, man. probably those
are the ones have a trading psychology
course to sell you.
Next up, you don't need to predict what
the markets will do in order to be a
profitable trader. I know that sounds
kind of, you know, weird, right? But
Rainer, don't I need to, you know,
predict what the markets will do in
order to make a profit?
No, not quite. And in fact, I like to
share with you an example. As you can
see, I'm a fan of, you know, sharing
examples to break down concepts so you
understand the logic behind it. So,
here's another example. So, imagine
this. Imagine you have a trading system
that wins 60% of the time. And follow
along with me. Let's say you have a
account size of $10,000. Your average
gain is $100 and your average loss is
$100. So, in other words, this trading
system has a 1:1 risk-to-reward ratio.
And on average, you earn 1% on your
trades. And on average, your loss is
also about 1% on your trades. But you
have an H because of your winning rate,
60%. And if you recall, I shared with
you earlier the expectancy formula, it's
over here. And if you plug in the
numbers into the formula, you know that
E is $20. This means that you can expect
to make an average of $20 per trade. Now
let's go back to the part earlier where
I say that you don't need to predict to
profit. So as you know to simplify
things if you have a 60% winning rate on
average if you take 100 trades about 60
of them is going to be a winners and 40%
of them will be losers. So I've
simplified this further. I I'm not going
to you know give 100 trading examples.
This is just a potential outcome of 10
trades. So this is scenario number one.
Let's say for this scenario first trade
is a winner winner winner winner winner
winner. The first six trades are winning
trades followed by four losing trades
over here. Now if you know that your
expectancy on average each each trade
you will make $20. You know that after
these 10 trades you'll be up $200. And
in fact if you don't believe me you just
plug in the numbers. Let's say average
gain over here is $100. You know that
you have six winners in a row. Total is
$600 minus the four losers which gives
you a net loss I mean a total loss of
400. End up you'll be $200 ahead. So
again first scenario you'll be up you'll
be up about $200. Let's look at the
second scenario. This time around you
encountered four losses in a row. one
two three four followed by six winning
trades. Again, if you do the math, you
will be up around $200, right? So, this
$200 is not guaranteed. It's just there
about average, right? In the real world
of trading, the number will be slightly
higher, lower and whatnot. Okay? So, if
you do the math, you will be up about
$200 for this scenario number two. And
finally, the third scenario, same thing.
If you have, let's say, three winners in
a row, you're going to get $300.
then followed by four losing trades. You
minus 400
and then finally you have another three
winners in a row plus 300 and up you're
going to be making about $200 in profit
as well. And I'm showing with you
showing you this three examples is to
let you know that you don't need to
predict in order to profit because can
you predict that hey you know these four
next four trades are going to be loser.
You can't. You have no idea what's going
to happen next. Likewise can you predict
that the first the next six trades
they're going to be winning trades? You
can't. And then let's say after the next
six winning trades you get four losing
trades. Are you able to predict that?
You can't. You can't predict the outcome
on any individual one trade. But, and
this is important, pay attention. But if
you have a proven trading system that
work, if you have a positive expectancy,
all you need to do is to let your
trading system do the work. All you need
to do is to let your age play out. All
you need to do is to follow the rules of
your trading system. And given long
enough timeline, given a sufficiently
large sample size of trades, you will
come out ahead. Does it make sense? You
don't have to predict what the market
will do over the next trade, the next
few trades. Because if you have an edge,
if you have sound risk management, if
you have the discipline to follow the
rules, eventually you will come out
ahead.
I'm pretty sure that at one stage or
another,
you are or you were trying to find the
best trading strategy.
I'm here to tell you right now, don't
bother. Don't bother trying to find the
best trading strategy. And why? The
reason is simple. Every trading strategy
is designed to profit from a specific
pattern in the market. Let me explain.
Say for example, a trend following
strategy. Trend following usually does
well when the markets are trending. When
it's in an uptrend, you write the
uptrend higher. If it's in a downtrend,
you can write the downtrend lower. And
of course, if the market is rangebound,
choppy, false breakout, a trend follower
will not do so well in such a market
environment.
On the other hand, you have a mean
reversion trading strategy. A mean
reversion trading strategy looks to buy
when the market is temporarily oversold.
Something like let's say market or
rather the stock goes up comes down goes
up comes down and then it's currently
oversold massive selloff. What a mean
reversion trader will do. You'll buy in
anticipation that the stock price will
bounce up higher and then you sell for a
profit. So this what is what mean
reversion trading is about buying low
selling high or selling high and then
buying back at a lower price. So these
are two different trading strategies and
none of them okay none of them works all
the time they just simply work
when the market conditions are favorable
to that and if that's the case if you
agree with what I just said then I'm
sure you can agree that market
conditions they change all the time
right as you can see right the S&P 500
this year last few years could be in an
uptrend and you never know whether it's
going to go back into a bare market like
what we've seen in the 08 09 financial
crisis or it goes into a range a choppy
market etc. The market change all the
time. You just look at any charts on the
daily, the weekly time frame, you can
see that the market conditions is always
changing. And if you agree with that
statement, then you would know that no
trading strategy will work all the time
because market conditions change all the
time. So this is why I say don't bother
finding the best trading strategy. Don't
bother finding something that works all
the time because it doesn't exist.
The good news is
I found something pretty close.
Now let me explain to you how this
works. So earlier I've shared with you
two types of trading strategies, right?
Trend following and mean reversion.
Trend following does well when the
market is trending. Mean reversion you
usually would do well when market is
kind of like choppy in a range. Mean
reversion trading will do well. So if
you look at the results of this trading
system right this is a trend following
system
you can see that since 2000 it has
generated about 2900%.
And if you break this trading system
down the results to a year on year and
month results. You can see that
over the last 24 years we have a few
losing years notably in I think this is
2009. This one is probably 2012 here and
2023. And what's interesting about trend
following is that it usually does very
well during a crisis period. For
example, this is the dotcom bubble up
about 23%. 2008 financial crisis up
about 80%. COVID up this case 23%,
Russia Ukraine war 42%. So you can see
that when there is crisis, when there is
panic in the markets, trend follower
usually would do well during this
period.
Next up, we have the mean reversion
trading system up about 8,000% since
2000. And again, if you break this down
on a year-on-year, month-on-month basis,
you can see that again, the mean
reversion trading system, it doesn't
make money every year. We have a couple
of losing years over here in this is
2014 and over here 2022 over here. 2022
no surprise because this is a stock mean
reversion trading system and 2022 I
believe the S&P 500 was you know down
for the year was a bare market. So with
this in mind, if you look at this,
right, this are the two trading systems
I've shared with you earlier, the trend
following and the mean reversion one.
And what you're seeing over here is the
yearly returns over the last 24 years.
You can see that the trend following
system had one, two, three, and four
losing years. And the mean reversion
trading system had two losing years. So
now the question is this how how can you
reduce the chance of
experiencing a losing year? How can you
reduce or rather increase the chance of
making money almost every year
regardless whether it's a bull market, a
bare market or during a recession. So
the secret is this. The secret is let's
say for example you have $10,000 trading
capital. You don't want to put all
10,000 into let's say the trend
following system or the mean reversion
trading system. Instead, you want to
split it. Let's say 50% into trend
following and 50% into mean reversion
trading. And when you do that, this is
where the magic happens. Boom. Right?
Look at this. If you look at it at this
column over here, the column says net,
you can see that you are profitable
almost every single year, whether it's a
bull market, a bare market, or even
during a recession. The one year that
you lost money is in 2023, down about 5%
for the year. But the point I'm trying
to make is that no trading strategy
works all the time because market
conditions change all the time. But when
you have multiple trading strategies at
your disposal, you have a good chance of
making a profit almost every single
year. And by the way, if you want to
learn more about trend following systems
or min reversion trading system, I have
this book over here called
trading systems that work, you can grab
a copy at this link over here. Just go
down to trading systemsbook.com and you
can grab a copy of this book and it's
like what 17 bucks and you get three
proven trading systems that work the
exact entries, exits, trading trading
rules, all given to you and you're
backed by a 180 days money back
guarantee. If you're not happy or
whatsoever, you can just, you know,
email us and we'll happily refund you in
full. So there's zero risk for you in
grabbing a copy of this book called
Trading Systems that work.
Here's a quick story of my own trading
journey. So, I started out in the forex
markets where I was on baby pips and I
came across this thread, someone
teaching a Ballinger band trading
strategy, right? Wait for the price to
come to the lows of the Ballinger band,
you buy. And when the price reach ups
higher, touches the high of the
Ballinger band, you sell profit. So,
that's what I did. So made some money at
the start only to lose it all later on.
So then I figured to myself, hm, maybe
the strategy isn't working. So that's
where I started looking around and came
into the trading world of indicators.
You know, I realized that, wow, there's
so many different tools I can use, not
just Ballinger bands. I have RSI, MACD,
Fibonacci. So I tried all this different
tools and guess what? Made some money,
but all in all, I lost more money than I
made. Then that's where I hop onto the
world of patterns, harmonic patterns,
volume. And this exact process rins
repeat itself.
So the big breakthrough that I got was
when I read this book called Market
Wizards by Jack Schwagger. So in this
book, Jack, he mentioned that every
successful trader that he has
interviewed, they all have an H in the
markets. So that was my first
breakthrough. Oh, I need an edge in the
markets. The second breakthrough came
right when I realized that in order to
know whether you have an edge in the
markets, you need to take a strategy, a
concept and
to turn it into a fixed set of rules.
From this fixed set of rules, then you
need to test to test how this rules has
performed whether you know through
forward testing or back testing. For for
me my preference I like to back test. So
this is why you need to test your
trading system. So for me I like to go
with the approach of back testing which
is simply back testing a strategy across
the past data to see if it works or not.
So I trade a lot of the stock markets.
So I like to back test over the last 10
15 20 years across different market
cycles in a bull market a bare market
and see how it has fared over time. And
what you're trying to do is to answer
this very simple question. If I had
traded this system before, if I had
taken this set of rules that I've
created before and trade it in the past,
would I have made money? And the reason
that you want to do this is because it
allows you to validate your strategy, to
help you identify the strength and
weaknesses of the strategy and to build
confidence. Let me prove it to you. So,
have a look at this equity curve over
here. Imagine this. Imagine I told you
imagine your name is Raina. Hey Raina,
I've just developed this trading system
and this is the equity curve of the back
test results over the last 24 25 years
since 2000 it has made about 8,000%
return about an average of a 18 19%
annual return. Now let me ask you is
this something that you would at least
give it a shot to trade it in the live
markets assuming you know the logic and
the rules behind this system and you
think it's sound. Will you at least give
this system a chance to put some a
little bit of real money on the line? I
think for most traders who look at this
equity curve, I think it's probably a
yes. At the same time, what if you come
across an equity curve that looks
something like this and I tell you,
"Hey, Raina, this is the results of my
trading system over the last 25 years.
It has lost 99% of your money over the
last 25 years. Would you want to trade
it?" Heck no. Right? I think nobody
wants to trade a trading system with
such horrendous results.
So this is why if you have the ability
to test your trading system ahead of
time, you would have saved yourself a
ton of time and money. And so this is
why it's so important to test, test, and
test. And of course, if you'd want to do
the back testing on your own, that's
where, you know, you can use uh leverage
the works of other traders like me,
right? where I wrote a book called
Trading Systems that work. Contains
three proven trading systems with the
complete trading rules, the back test
results all in the book as well. So I'll
put the link somewhere below this video.
You can check it out if you want.
So many traders think that in order to
make the big money in trading, they must
take huge risk to take big bets. That is
like someone who sees a wall and the
wall could possibly just be filled with
wet paint and they want to verify it. So
what does the person do? He take his
entire palm. The full palm and on the
wall instead of using one small finger
just to test whether if it's wet or not.
And of course with the full palm, right,
your entire palm is now filled with
pain. You want to get rid of it. You
smear it on your shirt and now you look
like a complete mess. And that's what
you're going to be a mess if you take
big risk in trading. You likely blow up
your trading account. So what you want
to do is this. Let me walk you through
the safe and consistent way to grow your
account to six or seven figures and
beyond.
So imagine this, right? Imagine, let's
say, I'm going to assume you guys
watching this are maybe in Singapore
like me, you have $20,000 somewhere to
fund your trading account. So let's say
you start with a $20,000 trading
account. Let's say you are 35 years old
this year and you can possibly grow your
account for the next 20 years. Even if
you're 45 or 55, you can as well, but
whatever. You grow your account for the
next 20 years. And let's say your
trading system strategy makes an annual
return of about 17% a year on average.
So after 20 years, how much will your
account be worth? You might be thinking,
Raina, I'm not an idiot. The answer is
the answer is listed over here. You're
right. Okay, the answer is that your
account will be worth $462,000
after 20 years, assuming you compound it
for the next 20 years at an average
return of 7 17% a year. Let's be honest,
this isn't life-changing money. So, what
else can you do about it? So, what else
you can do is this.
Let's assume that you're going to keep
your starting capital the same. You
compound for the next 20 years. Again,
you're not extending it and you're using
the same system with the same risk
management. So, the same 17% a year. And
the only difference that you're doing is
this time around you add an extra
$20,000 to your account each year. How
much difference would that make? So,
I'll give you like, you know, 5 seconds
to think this through. 1 3 4 5. Okay.
So, previously you saw that your account
would have been worth, I think, about
$462,000.
Now, by making this one simple tweak,
regularly adding funds to your account,
your account now will be worth, get
ready for it, it will be worth $3.5
million. I kid you not, you can even do
this compound interest calculation on
your own. So, can you see how powerful
this concept is? You didn't change your
trading system. You didn't take on more
risk. You didn't change strategy or
whatsoever. The only thing you did is to
regularly add funds to your account each
year.
Now, you might be thinking, "But Rainer,
if it's so easy, then why don't many
traders do it?" Well, because it's slow
and boring. And here's my question to
you. Would you rather take it slow and
boring and to make the big money or go
fast and exciting and lose everything?
Now you might be wondering but Raina
profitable traders they are smart they
have an above average IQ
they are math wizards
well I'm here to tell you that that is
not true take me for example I have a
very average IQ if you ask me I think my
IQ is just 100 slightly above there
about I've got a GPA of about two and I
failed math in school. You can see over
here this is my report card back in
school. Fil almost every subjects out
there except English.
So here's the thing, right? If wheats
and IQ they are not essential as long as
you're average I think that's good
enough. Then what is essential? What is
required?
It's this.
You must commit. You must commit to
number one, finding an edge in the
markets
to find a trading system that you know
will yield a positive result in the long
run. And if you struggle with that,
don't worry because you can go down to
my website over here, tradinger.com.
Okay? And this guide over here right at
this website you scroll down scroll down
a little bit and look for this guide
called the essential guide to systems
trading. In this guide I will share with
you my approach to finding proven agents
in the market without trial and error
and without you know wasting time going
around in circles. So download this
guide. I will share with you the red
formula. This is the formula that I use
to get new trading ideas ideas that give
me an edge in the market so I can
develop trading systems that work. Okay,
so I'll put a link somewhere below this
video so you can grab a copy of this
guide.
Next one, you must commit to managing
your risk. And it's it's not difficult.
You know, risk management, I think I've
talked about it earlier. It's one of the
it's the lowest hanging fruit in trading
because it's going to be relevant on day
one as well as on your last day of
trading. and give yourself 45 minutes to
an hour and that's it. You will
understand the math behind risk
management and it will pay dividends for
the rest of your life. So commit to
this. Next, you must commit to following
your rules. And based on what I've seen,
the smarter someone is, the more they
tend to struggle because they think that
they are smarter than everyone else.
They are better than everyone else. They
can dictate the rules. they know when to
break the rules and that's where trouble
seeps in. So, if you're average,
congratulations, right? If you're
average, then this should be easy for
you because you know that you're not the
smartest out there. You have a proven
system that works. You don't want to
reinvent the wheel. You just follow the
rules and that's how you get results.
So, congrats on being average. Yay.
Right. Finally, being average is a it's
a blessing because once you have an age
and risk management, you know, being
average will help you better follow the
rules.
And let's say you are the unfortunate
few. You are blessed with talent, with,
you know, smartness, IQ, and you
struggle with following the rules. Then
here's a tip for you. What you can do is
to find an accountability partner,
right? Every time you break your rules,
guess what? You bring your partner to
shopping, right, with a budget of $500.
And I'm pretty sure, right, very soon,
you'll have no issues with discipline.
Try that, right? Let me know how it
works for works out for you. Okay? And
next one, you need to commit to
learning.
So you don't need a high IQ to learn.
You just need a thirst for knowledge.
And remember, you are always a student
of the markets. Regardless of where you
are in your trading journey, not yet
profitable, break even, very profitable
for the last 10 years, you are still a
student of the markets. The learning
never ends. And finally, commit. Commit
to figuring out. There's a lot of
things to figure out in life.
as well as in trading. In trading, no,
nobody's going to spoon feit you, you
know, what exactly to do step by step
because nobody is as invested as you.
So, here's the thing. You don't need a
high IQ to figure things out. You've got
ChatGpt, Google, YouTube, library,
books. If you ask the right questions, I
100% believe you will get the right
answers, but only if you commit to
figuring things out on your own. But you
must put in effort. Yeah. Don't expect
things to be handed on a silver platter
because it's your money that's on the
line and nobody cares about your money
more than you. So trading isn't a genius
IQ test. Let's face it, right? It's a
marathon. You don't win by being the
fastest brain in the room. You win by
not giving up.
So look at this.
On average, you take 11 years to be a
doctor. And depending on the type of
doctor you want to be, if you want to be
a neurosurgeon, you probably will take
even longer.
7 years to be a lawyer, 5 years to be an
engineer. And guess what? You get into
trading and within a year, you expect to
be profitable, to generate another
source of income, to quit your full-time
job, you know, sip a cup of pinina
coladas by the beach and call it quits,
right? Life is good.
doesn't quite work that way because if
that's the case then there will be no
more doctors, lawyer, engineer in the
world. Everybody's going to be traders
getting drunk by the beach. Yeah. So, so
that's a reality check. So, if you ask
me,
as a trader, you will likely go through
five stages in your trading journey. And
I want to walk you through what these
five stages are. So, number one, I can
better manage your expectations. And
number two, you know what to expect in
each and every stage of your journey and
how to kind of shortcut your learning
curve and jump to the next stage, right?
As efficiently as possible. Let's go.
Stage number one is what I call the
hyper newbie stage. So at this stage,
you feel very excited. You have high
hopes about trading of the possibilities
out there. You know, financial freedom,
you know, quitting your job. You don't
have to answer to bosses. Oh man, you
know, life it's beautiful. Okay. So you
you are very eager to learn everything
and anything about trading and at this
stage you start to realize man you lose
one trading account you lose another
trading account and then and then you
stumble upon and realize you've been
blowing up multiple trading account and
trading isn't as easy as it seems. So at
this stage you kind of realize man I
need proper risk management and once you
realize that you move on to stage two
which is what I call the risk manager.
So at this stage,
once you master risk management, you've
stopped blowing up your trading account.
But the problem you face at this stage
is that you realize you're still not
making a profit. In fact, you're still
losing consistently over time. Yes, you
don't have big massive losses, but this
little small losses starts to add up,
right? And you're suffering death by a
thousand cuts. And at this point you
would then realize you need something
which is what what I call earlier or
shared earlier an age. You need an age
in the markets. So once you realize you
need an age in the markets you would
move on to stage three. This stage I
call it the lone ranger stage because at
this stage you have probably you know
one two three years trading experience
under your belt and you've learned so
much stuff about trading. You know price
action chart patterns trading strategies
systems volume profile etc.
But still you're not seeing the results
that you want. But still you're not able
to turn your knowledge into profits.
That's the problem that you have.
So at this point, right, this is where
you realize that you need a trading
system that works. You need to develop a
trading system that gives you an edge in
the markets and either through back
testing or forward testing. Okay. So
this stage personally is the stage that
I was stuck in the longest. But once you
graduate from this stage, you move on to
stage number four, profitable trading
stage. Give yourself a pat on the back
because at this stage only a small
percentage of traders will make it. So
if you're here, be proud of yourself. I
am very proud of you because
you know, good job. So at this stage,
you have been profitable over the last
12 months. So your equity curve in your
trading account, you know, it's kind of
going up higher over the last 12 months.
And the problem you face at this stage
is you realize that your strategy has
its limitations. It's not going to go up
nice smooth equity curve over 12 months.
It's going to go up jagged goes down
then breaks up higher then makes a
pullback range and then breaks out
higher once again. So this is where you
realize that your strategy has its
limitations because it only works well
in certain market conditions. So this is
where you realize you need to adopt
multiple trading strategies so you can
profit in different market conditions
which is the holy grail that I shared
with you earlier. And when you realize
that this is where you move on to stage
five, the business owner stage. At this
stage you are a profitable trader and
you want to take your trading to the
next level. So what you're doing at this
stage is you research new trading
systems, new strategies. You're raising
capital to grow the size of your account
maybe through managing funds. I hope not
not taking on debt right from the banks
and whatnot. Yeah. And you're using
technology to make your trading life
easier maybe through the use of
automation. So at this stage you're kind
of like a business owner, right? Running
multiple trading strategies, developing
new strategies, automating it and you
have and you are treating business
rather trading as a business. So a quick
recap this is the life cycle of a
trader, right? Number one, you start off
with the hyper newbie stage. Then you
move on to the risk manager stage, the
loan ranger, the profitable trader and
then finally business owner. Now some of
you are thinking you know Rainer you
know when can I get to the profitable
trading stage? I mean it really depends
on how open you are to learning and
receiving feedback but generally most
traders that I see if they have the
right tools resources and mindset they
could get there you know two years two
and a half years that's I would say the
fast side. the slow one I think maybe or
I wouldn't say slow but the average
people will probably take you know three
or four years or more because there's a
lot of lessons there's a lot of things
that you have to experience yourself you
have to feel it you sorry not feel it to
fail you have to feel at it
only then can you move on forward
because if you don't fail then you won't
have the feedback you won't realize the
thing that's holding you back yeah so
that is the life cycle of a trader
So let me share with you my thoughts. So
recently I have thoughts of you know
getting a lended property in Singapore
because the property market in Singapore
is very strong and lended properties
have strong capital appreciation and on
top of it right because you're buying a
property you can take a loan from a bank
and leverage your returns. So you you
know in landed in Singapore it's
reasonable to make an extra 10 15%
capital appreciation right on top of the
capital that's invested for lender
property in Singapore.
So I shared this with my wife and she
said she said this
for what?
Then I said to make more money and then
she replied
for what?
And then crickets.
That's because right me and my wife we
both have come to an agreement that
money is a means to an end. And she gave
me a reminder that money
is a tool. It's a means to an end. You
don't want to end up chasing more and
more just because everyone else is doing
it
because what's going to happen is that
you will miss the forest for the trees.
So, so thank you darling right for that
timely reminder.
So, trading is a means to an end. But
the question is for you is what does the
end look like for you? So, let me share
with you my my version of it and you
know you can go back and think through
about yourself. So for me, trading
allows me to better provide for my
family so they don't have to go hungry
and I can give them a better quality of
life. You know, if let's say one day
YouTube decides to ban my account
because I go, "Hey, hey, what's up my
friends?" Guess what? Trading still
gives me a reliable source of income
right from the markets. Next, trading
allows me to be present
for my family and children because for
me, trading takes me less than 20
minutes a day and I am very involved
with my children's lives and the things
that they are doing dayto-day. This
allows me to help shape their character,
impart the right values, the right
knowledge, and to help them become
good adults to contribute back to
society when they are older.
Trading also helps me to realize that
money, they are just digits, numbers on
the screen, and I'm not defined by how
big or small those
digits are. Okay, remember this. You're
not defined by what you have. Doesn't
matter whether you are living in the
bungalow or in a small house. It doesn't
matter. You are defined by who you are.
Because if you know who you are deep
down, you know what's your purpose. What
is your contribution? That's all that
matters. And some people just never
figure that out because
they're always chasing for more and
more, being manipulated by the digits,
the money that they have in their bank
account, which at the end of the day
really, you can't take it to the
afterlife.
Trading also allows me to make money my
slave and not to be a master.
Okay? Okay. In other words, right, money
is a slave to me and I'm not treating it
as my master. So, I can use it to spread
God's love and to help those in need
because it is a very rewarding a
fulfilling experience when you help some
random stranger on the street just
because
you want to give them hope. It's a very
positive, happy feeling. If you've never
tried it before, I encourage you to do
so so you can know what I mean because
it is like donating 10 bucks and that 10
bucks will bring you so much happiness
that there's no other way to spend that
10 bucks and to derive that level of
happiness. You can buy, you know, five
plates of chicken rice, okay? You can't
get five plates of chicken rice for 10
bucks, but it's the best $10 that you
can spend to get
that high level of happiness.
Okay, so this is what trading means to
me. So to end it off right, my question
to you is this. What does trading means
to you? Leave a comment below this video
and let me know your thoughts. Now let's
do a quick recap. Number one, your
trading system must have an edge in the
markets because without an age, nothing
else matters. You can have the best risk
management, the best trading psychology,
and guess what? you still will not be a
profitable trader. That's how important
it is to have an age. Next one, master
risk management. This is the lowest
hanging fruit that you can tackle right
now that will pay dividends for the rest
of your trading career. It's not
difficult. 45 minutes to an hour is all
you need. And risk management will allow
you to leave to fight another day
through the darkest times, through 10
losing trades in a row, through a losing
streak.
Number three, trading psychology is not
the answer. If right now you are an
unprofitable trader, you are losing
trader, a break even trader,
high chance it's nothing to do with your
trading psychology. Very high chance is
number one and number two. If you focus
on finding an edge and your risk
management, you'll realize that your
trading psychology will naturally fall
into place. So, so really right, I think
for most of you watching this right now,
trading psychology is likely not the
root cause as to why you're not a
profitable trader yet. I have faith in
you. So, it's yet. Number four, you
don't need to predict to profit. I've
shared with you that if you have an age
and sound risk management,
you can you may not know whether the
next one trade, two trade, three trades
is a winning or losing trades. But what
I can assure you is is that if you have
an age and risk management, you will be
profitable still in the long run. That's
the power of having an age. That's the
power of having an age with sound risk
management and the discipline to follow
your rules. You don't need to predict
whether the next trade will be a winner
or loser. But you know in the long run
you will be a profitable trader. Number
five, don't bother finding the best
trading strategy. Why? Because it
doesn't exist.
is that you know market conditions
change all the time and that's why no
trading strategies is going to work all
the time. Number six, the next best
thing you can do is to have multiple
trading strategies. So this way you can
profit in different market condition.
Strategy for a bull market, strategy for
a bare market, strategy for a range
market. You can cover all the different
bases. Number seven, you must test your
trading system so you know whether it
works or not. You can even do it via
back testing which is my favorite
approach or forward testing which is
more for discretionary traders. Number
eight, compound your returns and
regularly advance because this is how
the big money is made. I always like to
say that trading is not a get-rich quick
scheme. is more of a get-rich slow skip
and slow but not very slow because you
give it like 10 20 years you would have
compound a pretty decent sum of money
that will put you way ahead of your
peers had they not been in trading or
investing
number nine your commitment is more
important than your wheats you don't
need an IQ of 150 you don't need a GPA
of three or four take me for example I
have a very average IQ very mediocre GPA
But still, if you have the commitment,
if you persevere, if you outwork
everyone else, I believe you can make it
as well. Number 10, go slow to go far.
I've shared with you the five different
stages of trading and hopefully you know
what it takes to get from one stage to
the next and to better manage
expectations along the way. And last but
not least, trading. Trading is a means
to an end. Everyone wants to do trading
because they want to make more money.
But remember this, money is just a tool.
Don't make money your slave. Make it
serve you. And what does having more
money means to you? What does this
financial freedom means to you? To
different people, it means different
things, right? Money could be used to
help others. Money could be used to
improve the quality of life of their
family and loved ones. Money could be
used to be a blessing to those in need.
Whatever it means to you, trading is a
means to an end. So don't forget that.
Don't get so sucked up in the world of
making more and more and more till you
miss the forest for the trees and you
realize that at the end of it all you
kind of have led a life which is you
know very superficial without really
much to show for or or without knowing
who you really are inside because you
are so
busy chasing the material stuff that you
lose your
soul along the way. Yeah.
So with that said, if you want to learn
more about my trading approach, systems
trading, then again, you can go and grab
a copy of this guide, which I highly
recommend. It's called the essential
guide to systems trading. I talked about
this one earlier. This is where you will
learn how you can actually develop your
own trading strategies, your own trading
systems, how to get new ideas, plus I'll
even share with you a simple trend
following system that works so you can
profit in bull and bare markets even
during a recession. So the link is just
go down to my website
tradingwithrao.com, click on this orange
button and and I'll send this guide to
your email for free. So with that said,
I wish you good luck, good trading, stay
safe. I will talk to you soon.